A Guide to the Larry McBryde Collection on the John McLaren McBryde Family, 1859-2013
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Larry McBryde Collection on the John McLaren McBryde Family, 1859-2013
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2013-024
0.94 Cubic Feet; 3 boxes
The Larry McBryde Collection on the John McLaren McBryde Family, 1859-2013, contains materials concerning John McLaren McBryde, Sr., his brother Robert James McBryde, and their descendants. Primarily, the collection contains photographs, letters, family histories, and biographies about McBryde, Sr., who was president of Virginia Tech from 1891 thru 1907.
McBryde family
McBryde, John McLaren, 1841-1923
McBryde, Larry
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Larry McBryde Collection on the John McLaren McBryde Family were donated to Special Collections in multiple accessions in 2013. Additional materials were donated to Special Collections in May 2019.
Biographical Note
John McLaren McBryde (January 1, 1841-March 20, 1923) was born in Abbeville, South Carolina to Susan McLaren and John McBryde, a Scottish cotton merchant. In December of 1858, John McLaren McBryde enrolled in South Carolina College (later the University of South Carolina) in Columbia, South Carolina. He later transferred to the University of Virginia in 1859, leaving in 1861 to fight in the Civil War for the Confederacy. Having joined the military, McBryde was stationed on both Sullivan and Morris Islands, reportedly seeing the first shot fired on Fort Sumter. In 1862, McBryde contracted typhus fever and was forced to leave the army, but went on to work for the Treasury Department of the Confederate States of America in Richmond, Virginia. In September of 1963, McBryde married Cora Bolton, with whom he later had six children.
Following the end of the Civil War, McBryde ran a large farm named Branchland in Charlottesville, Virginia. During this time, he published numerous articles on the subject of agriculture, gaining him the attention that eventually lead to his appointment as a Professor of Agriculture and Botany at the University of Tennessee in 1879. In 1882, McBryde was offered a chair at the South Carolina College, where he remained until 1891, expanding it into a university after becoming president. In 1891, South Carolina University was again reduced to a college and its agricultural department moved to Clemson, leading to McBryde's acceptance of the Presidency at the Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College (VAMC).
During his time at Virginia Tech, McBryde divided the college into separate departments, expanded the curriculum, oversaw the installation of an infirmary and a new water system, added dormitories and faculty housing, and increased enrollment from 135 students in 1891 to 727 by 1903. After his retirement in 1907, McBryde was the first person elected president emeritus for the college, eventually becoming known as "the father of VPI." In 1923, McBryde died at his son's home in New Orleans but was returned to Blacksburg, Virginia for burial.
Scope and Content
The Larry McBryde Collection on the John McLaren McBryde Family, 1859-2013, contains materials concerning John McLaren McBryde, Sr., his brother Robert James McBryde, and their descendants, including John McLaren McBryde, Jr., Charles N. McBryde, Robert J. Davidson (the son-in-law of McBryde, Sr.), Meade Bolton McBryde, Sgt. John McLaren McBryde, David Caldwell McBryde, and others. The collection contains five series, organized by subject and subdivided chronologically.
Series I contains the papers of John McLaren McBryde, Sr., and his immediate family, dating from 1859 through 1930. Items include photographs and newspaper articles relating to McBryde's life and service at Virginia Tech, a Petersburg Railroad Pass during McBryde's Conderate service, a Sweet Briar College program, newspaper clippings related to the colleges he worked at, and an unbound photograph album (20 leaves) with photographs of the University of South Carolina, Washington and Lee University, and early images of the VPI campus and the surrounding town of Blacksburg. There are also letters to McBryde, including copies of correspondence pertaining to the University of Virginia's presidency, and to his son Charles N. McBryde about him. Finally, legal documents, letters, and resolutions relate to McBryde's death.
Series II contains items belonging to John McLaren McBryde, Jr., dated 1904 thru 1947. Primarily, items pertain to his research, reminiscences, and biographies about his father. There are also postcards to him and his wife of Blacksburg, Charlottesville, and Hollins, Virginia.
Series III contains a c. 1905 photograph of and 1926 memorial to Robert James McBryde, the brother of John McLaren McBryde, Sr.
Series IV consists of newspaper clippings, obituaries, and curriculum vitae, dated [1916?] thru 2013, for other McBryde Family members, including Robert J. Davidson, Meade Bolton McBryde, and the descendants of John McLaren McBryde, Sr., and Robert James McBryde. There is also a 1972 invitation sent to Sgt. John McLaren McBryde for the dedication ceremony of McBryde Hall at Virginia Tech in 1972.
The fifth and final series is undated genealogy of the McBryde Family. Several family trees and four handwritten volumes of the Chronicles of the McBryde Family by David Caldwell McBryde are included, along with partial photocopies and digital copies of the volumes on DVD.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into series by subject, and each series is arranged chronologically.
Series I: John McLaren McBryde, Sr., and Family
Series II: John McLaren McBryde, Jr.
Series III: Robert James McBryde
Series IV: Other McBryde Family Members
Series V: Genealogy
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Records of the Office of the President, John McLaren McBryde, RG 2/5
Polly Ashelman Collection on the John McLaren McBryde Family, Ms2019-017
Janet Barnhill Collection on Cora Bolton McBryde, Ms2016-019
McBryde House Specification Records, Ms1999-010
Index Terms
Subjects:
University History; University Archives
Persons:
Davidson, Robert J., Dr.; McBryde family; McBryde, Charles Neil, Dr., 1872-1962; McBryde, David Caldwell, 1845-1923; McBryde, John McLaren, 1841-1923; McBryde, John McLaren, 1870-1956; McBryde, Robert James, 1843 or 1845 to 1916
Organizations:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute
Contents List
- Series I: John McLaren McBryde, Sr., and Family, 1859-1930
  - South Carolina College Examination Results, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Confederate Petersburg Rail Road Pass, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Articles by John McLaren McBryde on Agriculture, 1883, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Articles from South Carolina College, 1885, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Articles on Agriculture from Mississippi College, 1887, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Unbound Photograph Album of University of South Carolina, 1888-1900 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Unbound Photograph Album of Lexington, Richmond, and Blacksburg, including Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College, 1889-1891 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Copy of biography on President McBryde from the 1899 Bugle yearbook (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs and Film Negatives of the John McLaren McBryde, Sr. Family, 1902-c. 1920s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence regarding the University of Virginia Presidency, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter from Archer Phlegar to John McLaren McBryde, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Retirement of John McLaren McBryde, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Articles from Sweet Briar College, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sweet Briar College Program, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook of Newspaper Articles, 1911-1923 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Last Will and Testament of John McLaren McBryde, Sr. (photocopy), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Obituaries for John McLaren McBryde, Sr., 1923 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Condolences, Resolutions, and Funeral Information for John McLaren McBryde, Sr., 1923 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letter from Charles N. McBryde to Charles W. Badney about his father's appearance, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series II: John McLaren McBryde, Jr., 1904-1947
  - Post Cards to Mrs. and Dr. John McLaren McBryde, Jr. of Blacksburg, Charlottesville, and Hollins, Virginia, 1904-1907 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - John McLaren McBryde, Jr.'s reminiscences and biographies on John McLaren McBryde, Sr., 1937, 1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Research of John McLaren McBryde, Jr. on John McLaren McBryde, Sr., 1944-1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series III: Robert James McBryde, c. 1905, 1926
  - Photograph of Dr. Robert J. McBryde, c. 1905 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Article, "Memorial to Dr. McBryde" [Dr. Robert James McBryde], 1926-12 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Other McBryde Family Members, [1916?]-2013
  - Newspaper Articles on Robert J. Davidson, [1916?], 1927 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Obituaries and CVs for Descendants of John M. McBryde, Sr., and Robert J. McBryde, 1957-2013 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Meade Bolton McBryde Newspaper Articles, 1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Invitation to Sgt. John McLaren McBryde for Dedication of McBryde Hall, 1972-07-04 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series V: Genealogy, undated
  - Family Trees, undated (Box 2, Folder 11, Box 3)
  - Chronicles of the McBryde Family by David Caldwell McBryde, 4 vols., undated (Box 3)
  - Photocopy of McBryde Chronicles on Robert J. Davidson and John McLaren McBryde, Sr., undated (Box 3)
  - Digital Copies of the Chronicles, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)